<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Thejasvi Beleyur</title><link>localhost:8000/</link><description>Re-search, animals, computing</description><atom:link href="rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:thejasvib@gmail.com"&gt;Thejasvi Beleyur&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 07:59:36 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>first post!!</title><link>blog/first-post/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h5&gt;Hello!&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, and welcome to the first post of my blog. This is where I'm planning to write about science and scientific computing. This is a somewhat informal venue
to discuss some ideas, &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="blog/first-post/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/first-post/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 07:58:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Universal data formats</title><link>blog/2_universal_data_formats/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm still trying to get through an old but (&lt;em&gt;I think&lt;/em&gt;) cool analysis for a manuscript 
that's over five years in the making now. The code in the manuscript
itself reflects the need for mutiple coding platforms and how each of them 
bring its own superpowers with it. All of the image analysis results in the project
has been done in MATLAB. The stats and analyses have been executed and documented
in R with Markdown notebooks. A collaborator did some additional analyses in 
MATLAB recently and sent over some new results. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would have all been fine, and I probably  wouldn't have even written the post if &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="blog/2_universal_data_formats/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/2_universal_data_formats/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 07:27:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>I need to finish this analysis for a manuscript that's *X* years old (...gasp)</title><link>blog/finish-this-analysis/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Updated : 2020-04-23 08:53:00
Category: data analysis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the social distancing measures implemented thanks to the COVID19 pandemic, I saw a whole wave of memes about academics thinking they'd get more productive. 
Now, that there're no more unnecessary meetings, teaching, or random interruptions from the workplace, it'd be great to &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; get back to doing &lt;strong&gt;SCAAAAAAINCE&lt;/strong&gt;. 
I myself, wasn't quite sure, as an end phase PhD student working at a mainly research institute, I can't quite complain about any of these things, although I will say I am beginning to enjoy the luxury and convenience of waking up, getting ready, and heading to the desk a few metres away. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="blog/finish-this-analysis/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/finish-this-analysis/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2020 06:26:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>So, how much do you really understand about (cool) topic X? (also, it's not you who's dumb, find the right source/teacher)</title><link>blog/4_how_much_do_you_really_understand/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Working in academia can be quite stressful. Handling the uncertainty  of where you'll be in the next few years, and whether you're competent enough at all
(impostor syndrome) are questions that're always hanging around. Even once you think you've understood something, five minutes later another thing'll come up to show that the mental model you had was actually &lt;em&gt;rather&lt;/em&gt; wrong. It can be very frustrating to put in a lot of effort, think of it as progress, and then back to square one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="blog/4_how_much_do_you_really_understand/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/4_how_much_do_you_really_understand/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 05:43:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Simultaneous code and docs: a safety net for your project</title><link>blog/working_with_documentation_on_the_go/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the past I always used to either badly document my code properly or ignore it completely. The focus was to get the job done and 
to get out. Nowadays, however, things have changed a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;, and I really only have the &lt;a href="http://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/stable/"&gt;Sphinx&lt;/a&gt; project to blame :P. Documenting
your code as it's being written helps in a bunch of ways, and the person who benefits from it the most is &lt;em&gt;futureyou&lt;/em&gt;. I've thanked 
&lt;em&gt;pastme&lt;/em&gt; a zillion times by now because the current project I'm working on has grown to be a more than a few files, and I was 
quite afraid of not being able to keep track of stuff. However, this time I really decided to write &lt;a href="https://numpydoc.readthedocs.io/en/latest/format.html"&gt;NumPy&lt;/a&gt; style docstrings on all functions that are more than a two lines, and with a little bit of Sphinx magic, and some &lt;a href="https://docs.readthedocs.io/en/stable/"&gt;ReadTheDocs&lt;/a&gt; hosting, the result is a beautiful webpage that  I keep visiting myself just because it's rewarding seeing something nice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="blog/working_with_documentation_on_the_go/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/working_with_documentation_on_the_go/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2020 06:20:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>To package or not to package?</title><link>blog/thought_on_releasing_a_package/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After having worked in a field for over a few years, and gotten comfortable with programming in the language of your  choice, you slowly begin to realise
that your work essentially always consists of a set of analyses/tasks which are used again and again. For me, experimentally this means, having scripts ready 
that will initiate recordings, playbacks, and saving of audio files for the experiments I do. In terms of simulations, it means writing a lot of code, typically
based on a bunch of acoustics paradigms that are described by a bunch of equations/assumptions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have of course read over and over again, that it's good practise to bundle all of your goodies into one place, and keep them as a package somewhere [REFS].
But why don't I do it yet? Right now, as an end-phase graduate student, I guess it's mainly because  each time I do this task, I'm not sure when I'll actually
have to do it again. The effort of trying to create a common framework and plan all the basic experimenta/computational tasks to be implemented doesn't pay  off. 
Writing a package, I realise  is as much about the single tiny  functions, as it is about the broad common concept and the sufficiently detailed documentation 
aroud it. If  I'm the only  one who's  going to use  it,  and am not even sure when - it's not worth the time :P. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="blog/thought_on_releasing_a_package/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/thought_on_releasing_a_package/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 06:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Better Science through good code</title><link>blog/pep_talk/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Beautiful is better than ugly,
  .... 
  ....
  Simple is better than complex.
  ....
  ....
  Readability counts.
  ....
  ....
  Errors should never pass silently
  ....
  If the implementation is hard to explain, it's a bad idea.
  If the implementation is easy to explain, it may be a good idea.
"&lt;/em&gt;
    -- Excerpts from the PEP-20, the &lt;a href="http://www.thezenofpython.com/"&gt;Zen of Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I began noticing after my transition to Python was the fact that the internet seemed to constantly throw words like 
'PEP', and 'coding conventions', 'naming conventions' and 'line lengths' and the lot. My initial reaction was to ignore them and continue coding
the way I had been. Back then I had been writing programs and hacking other peoples code for the past six years. I  thought  'Okay, this  is coding. What more is there?'. Classically naive thoughts eh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, it happened. No, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a magical  moment of expertise and awesomeness in coding, but the opposite of it all :P. An embarrasing, self-doubt seeding, waste of time experience, where I suddenly realised it all had to change. Having seeded  all this anticipation in you, I will now proceed to say this is a post for another time, suffice to say,  it was a professionally humbling experience, where I realised I had to go back and unlearn a bunch of things and learn a bunch concepts anew. This post is  about the power of one of those concepts: coding conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Good coding style is like correct punctuation: you can manage without it..."&lt;/em&gt; -- Hadley Wickham, &lt;a href="https://style.tidyverse.org/"&gt;The tidyverse style guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coding conventions are like  dialects  of a language in many ways. It's the umbrella term for a bunch of patterns that a group  of people use when they write code: how variables are named, the way the code is documented, or how the code is formatted. Each project typically has its own coding convention. In the Python community,  it seems like &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0008/"&gt;PEP-8&lt;/a&gt; is a common reference point. What is this PEP-8? The way I understand it, PEP-8 is the document which set out the coding conventions for all code that will be part of the main Python distribution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://numpy.org"&gt;NumPy&lt;/a&gt; docstrings and how following the patterns actually rewards you. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/pep_talk/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 05:37:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The coding language maketh not the science, but...</title><link>blog/the_programming_language/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to choice  of  programming language to get any task done,  people can sometimes have strong opinions. &lt;!-- TEASER-END --&gt;
I've seen tweets from authors reporting reviewers who wanted the stats/plots/something done in R, and being dismissive of it 
being done in any  other language. This is truly ridiculous, and this kind of attitude amounts to a weird, unhealthy kind 
of gate-keeping. What will come next, oh the code is only  compatible with a Windows OS, it should have been developed keeping 
a Unix OS in mind...or even more specific comments about which packages to use?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is, there is a feeling some members of the community have that certain computational tasks are well suited to be done 
with &lt;em&gt;insert favouriteprogramminglanguage&lt;/em&gt;. I find this attitude absurd and take it to be a form of irrational favoritism. If 
a piece of code is not in a coding language I use regularly, the only thing it means is that I may  not be familiar  with 
a whole bunch of cool concepts and ideas that the authors use. It doesn't mean the work is sub-standard. This argument cuts 
both ways, whether the language is an open-source or proprietary platform. If anything at all, if I have to read code written 
in an unfamiliar language and understand it - it needs to be well-documented! The user/reader needs  to understand what  is 
happening in the code irrespective of the actual for and while loops running under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documenting code well is not a trivial task,  and not something which can be done well over a couple of days. The closest task to documenting a codebase
 is writing a (scientific) manuscript. Things keep changing, you realise a bunch of things over a series of iterations, and 
even then there may be details lying around from the time you actually created the manuscript file itself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, okay, the programming language maketh not the science. A well-documented codebase is more capable of convincing an
audience of its own utility and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/the_programming_language/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 08:16:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>So, you do *everything* in Python?</title><link>blog/why_python/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"..and that was when Mowgli knew he would forever be safe in the comforting coils of Saamp, the Python"&lt;/em&gt;
-- &lt;em&gt;Not Rudyard Kipling, 1892&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Open your eyes, look up to the skies and see" *
&lt;/em&gt;--Queen, Not Rudyard Kipling, 1975 *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every now and then at a conference, someone might ask me what programming language all this stuff was done in. 
When I say Python, there's typically two reactions. One typical response is 'That's cool, I too use Python, which libraries...'
, and as you  can imagine, the conversation takes a very detailed trajectory. The other typical response is 'I see, yeah, everyone's using Python nowadays. My supervisor/whole lab uses &lt;em&gt;&lt;insert sixletterword&gt;&lt;/insert&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and so I'm kind of stuck at the moment'. My response to this statement is to strongly  urge the person to switch. Now is the best time to switch, and save yourself  time later etc. I  probably(definitely) end up sounding like a weird mix of concerned parent and preacher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I begin talking about the benefits of swithching to Python, I will make it clear upfront that the computer language maketh not the science. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="blog/why_python/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/why_python/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 23:15:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What you *could* do, but you shouldn't</title><link>blog/error_msgs/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"What gets you into trouble ain't what you don't know, but what you think you do, but ain't so"&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is about how good software should be like an honest person - who knows their area of competence before taking up a task &lt;em&gt;REPHRASE THISS-- IT'S TOO STRONG&lt;/em&gt;. 
We (myself included) often receive or write code to get things working, and then proceed to keep using it or share it eventually with our lab mates. 
Like anything in the course of life,  use-cases for the software may change. A new project comes up,  or someone (Person X) legitimately decides it'll be cool to try out this new experiment
and process the data with this awesome codebase.  Person X now triumphantly  sits in front of the computer...and waits for the code to  run through with anticipation .... and after a few seconds of anticipation,  out come the plots!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there's a twist to the story in that the results actually seem okay in the beginning, until Person X notices a bunch of weird details. Factor Z, a universal constant, is about 1.5 times more than it should - and this is too much. 
But the diagnostic plots look fine, and the  code ran!! What is happening??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many agonising hours later, Person X finally figures out that the Awesome Codebase has been a somewhat dishonest person. 
How is Awesome Codebase like a dishonest person you ask? Well, Person X figured out finally that Awesome Codebase was basically written to handle the analysis of Cool Experiments done to understand Factor Z using four Z-probes. What are Z-probes? They are the devices that measure the value of the Z-factor. Awesome Codebase can handle a wide variety of Z-probes, and that's why it's quite famous in its community. However, it  turns out Person X wanted to replicate  the experiments under the simplest possible conditions. Person X's experiment involves measurements with &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; Z-probes, instead of the standard five, six, or seven. 
In principle,  Person X, thinks - the only reason people haven't done it before is because they were being exta careful  in the early days, who needs &lt;strong&gt;four&lt;/strong&gt; Z-probes anyway??!!
But no, days later, Person X finds out that Awesome Codebase really wasn't built to handle three Z-probes at all! It is a logical impossibility given the equations and Science in the field of Z-factor studies. It turns out all Z-factor experiments have been done only with a prime number of Z-probes, ranging from 5 to 29, but no-one had  really thought of going below 5.
 If it is so  impossible, why didn't Awesome Codebase throw an error and stop everything dead in its tracks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the analogy isn't clear yet. Awesome Codebase has been like someone  who nods silently but enthusiastically  to the question 'Can you speak German, the people at the dinner we're going to don't speak much English ?'.
And then, when you meet with Awesome Codebase for dinner, Awesome Codebase says 'Gruesse Sie', 'Danke', 'Salz' in a burst, and then settles down quietly for the rest of  the evening. Yes, you  could argue, this person does know &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; German - but the question is can they handle a conversation?
Do they understand what is happening around them? Why are they not saying anything, do  they know saying these three things in a continuous string may be grammatically correct but socially unusual. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest question remains of course, that is - why  didn't my  acquaintancce just say they don't speak German well enough. You could have then made other plans.
And so, in analogy, if Awesome Codebase was not built to handle less than five Z-probes - it should have said it out loud, thrown a warning, or even better - thrown a nasty error saying exaclty that &lt;em&gt;Z-probe error, this codebase cannot handle &amp;lt;5 Z-probes!&lt;/em&gt;
Person X would have been happy, and moved on to find another equally awesome codebase, and  Awesome Codebase wouldn't have been dishonest. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a rant about how codebases are limited in their nature, it is a rant about the lack of documentation and clear communication to the user. 
All codebases are limited in their capabilities and are constrained by the historically envisioned use-cases. 
The use-cases will naturally change, but if the codebases capabilities don't match the requirements of the use-case -- this must be easily detectable!
The capabilities and limitations of a code base must be clearly highlighted in the form of a README or user manuals. If even these are not heeded or clear,  the true weapon to prevent misuse is throwing a clear error. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>blog/error_msgs/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 07:20:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>