<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Thejasvi Beleyur (Posts about Python, coding, scientific computing)</title><link>https://thejasvibr.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thejasvibr.github.io/categories/cat_python-coding-scientific-computing.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:thejasvib@gmail.com"&gt;Thejasvi Beleyur&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 09:15:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>So, you do *everything* in Python?</title><link>https://thejasvibr.github.io/blog/why_python/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"..and that was when Mowgli knew he would forever be safe in the comforting coils of Saamp, the Python"&lt;/em&gt;
-- &lt;em&gt;Not Rudyard Kipling, 1892&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Open your eyes, look up to the skies and see" *
&lt;/em&gt;--Queen, Not Rudyard Kipling, 1975 *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every now and then at a conference, someone might ask me what programming language all this stuff was done in. 
When I say Python, there's typically two reactions. One typical response is 'That's cool, I too use Python, which libraries...'
, and as you  can imagine, the conversation takes a very detailed trajectory. The other typical response is 'I see, yeah, everyone's using Python nowadays. My supervisor/whole lab uses &lt;em&gt;&lt;insert sixletterword&gt;&lt;/insert&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and so I'm kind of stuck at the moment'. My response to this statement is to strongly  urge the person to switch. Now is the best time to switch, and save yourself  time later etc. I  probably(definitely) end up sounding like a weird mix of concerned parent and preacher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I begin talking about the benefits of swithching to Python, I will make it clear upfront that the computer language maketh not the science. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://thejasvibr.github.io/blog/why_python/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://thejasvibr.github.io/blog/why_python/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 23:15:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>