<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Thejasvi Beleyur (Posts about research)</title><link>https://thejasvibr.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thejasvibr.github.io/categories/research.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:thejasvib@gmail.com"&gt;Thejasvi Beleyur&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 04:29:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Alpathrupthi - the key to sustained research?</title><link>https://thejasvibr.github.io/blog/alpathrupthi/</link><dc:creator>Thejasvi Beleyur</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;original post: 05/20, edits in 04/21&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost over half a decade ago, I was still in college/university and busy training my 
future scientist-self in the art of collaboration through evenings filled
with multi-player games. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that I really liked playing these games, it turned out I really ....&lt;em&gt;sucked&lt;/em&gt;.
My hand-eye coordination was too bad for fast paced first-person shooter games, and my sense of 
strategy for real-time strategy games was inadequate, to say the least. The problem 
was that we'd often play in teams,  and  so the people in my team would
suffer quite a bit thanks to  my incompetence :P. The main issue: my thresholds for satisfaction were low,
 and I was extremely happy whenever the most basic things worked out. In 
a first person shooter, this meant not dying and my ultimate strategy was to indiscrimately spray everything with bullets. In the strategy games, this
meant not being invaded, or succeeding in a minor takeover of a neighbouring village. On top of that, I was in many ways like the proverbial frog 
in boiling water. Many real-time strategy games require you to keep check of your kingdom's finances, labour power etc. I could never notice my kingdom
failing, and would ask for a loan from my team-mates after it was too late. Also, I never got better through the two years that we played :p. No matter
how badly we lost, I'd still be happy with something insignificant that had happened in the game. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one of these evenings, a friend of mine finally expressed his frustration and amusement by by calling me an &lt;em&gt;'alpathruptha'&lt;/em&gt;, and that phrase has somehow remained with me for a long time. &lt;em&gt;Alpathruptha&lt;/em&gt;, is a sanskrit word
(also used in Kannada) that describes someone who is easily satisfied, or with low ambition &lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://thejasvibr.github.io/blog/alpathrupthi/#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. My dear friend was
of course strongly focussing on my utter lack of drive and ambition. While I may be an &lt;em&gt;alpathruptha&lt;/em&gt;
 in certain parts of life, I constantly struggle with being dissatisfied with the progress in a project
or where it is at right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The origin of this flashback to the word now fail me, but it somehow lead me 
to think about how in some ways the more of an &lt;em&gt;alpathrutha&lt;/em&gt; one is, the 
better it might be while doing research. Especially while handling a new topic
or technical method, perhaps less is better? In some ways being thrilled at 
having survived the day, is a great incentive for coming back the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering how a lot of research in the initial phases is two steps front, ten steps back, a sense of &lt;em&gt;alpathrupthi&lt;/em&gt; is only appropriate perhaps. 
Perhaps it's also important to celebrate the realisation of failure. When you realise something is wrong with the code/equipment/results, maybe it should be 
considered an achievement in itself. Of course some might argue, this is nothing but &lt;em&gt;alpathrupthi&lt;/em&gt; embodified, you decide. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;alpathruptha&lt;/em&gt; also has the other more ascetically associated meanings: without great desire, one with low
expectations or easily satisfied. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://thejasvibr.github.io/blog/alpathrupthi/#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>research</category><guid>https://thejasvibr.github.io/blog/alpathrupthi/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>